{
    "tossups": [
        {
            "question": "This empire launched a failed invasion of Qanbaloh to gain access to luxury goods such as tortoise shells and ambergris. Cox et al traced mitochondrial DNA back to 30 founding mothers to determine that a group of settlers from this empire colonized Madagascar. George C\u0153d\u00e8s [seh-DEHS] revived modern scholarship on this empire, which the Taoist monk Y\u00ecj\u00ecng provided descriptive accounts of in his travelogues. The Buddhist Sailendra family ruled over both this empire and the neighboring\u00a0 (*) Medang Empire for a brief period of time.\u00a0 To weaken this empire\u2019s maritime power Rajendra Chola I launched naval raids against it, ultimately leading to the sack of its capital at Palembang. Controlling both the Sunda and Malacca Straits, for 10 points name this thalassocratic empire that ruled from Sumatra from the 7th through 13th centuries.",
            "answer": "Srivijaya Empire",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Two diplomats from this country name the expedition sent to convince Habibullah Khan to declare independence. A spy with the codename \u201cOren\u201d exposed a plot by this country to arm the Christmas Day Plot. This country funded the Ghadar Party\u2019s attempt to ship arms to India from the United States during the Annie Larsen Affair. While living in this country, (*) Roger Casement attempted to create an \u201cIrish Brigade\u201d to fight for Irish independence. Though not used for its intended purpose, Subhas Chandra Bose organized a unit of Indian soldiers in this country who had earlier been taken from the British army by this country\u2019s Afrika Korps. For 10 points, identify this country, whose efforts to undermine British colonial rule involved ministers like Arthur Zimmermann and Fritz von Papen.",
            "answer": "Germany (accept German Empire)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The site of Lapaha in this country contains a stone throne called the Maka Fa\u2019akinanga, which was designed so that an alert ruler could not be assassinated. The junior members of the ruling family of this country, or tehina, were sent abroad to establish their own political authority away from the capital, establishing a thalassocracy. This country lost much of its invested capital when former Bank of America financial advisor and honorary court jester (*) Jesse Bogdonoff lost almost all of the profit it had made selling passports to foreigners. The 20th century kingdom established in this modern country was made a protectorate of the British under its King George Tupou II in 1900 to prevent the spread of German influence from their nearby colony in Samoa. For 10 points, what is this country, a Polynesian monarchy governed from Nuku\u2019alofa?",
            "answer": "Kingdom of Tonga",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "W.H. Coltharp enlisted this institution without their knowing to help supply bricks for the construction of the bank of Vernal, Utah. A 1970 strike of employees of this institution in New York led to Operation Graphic Hand, in which their jobs were temporarily carried out by the military. An employee of this institution compiled a list of hotels, restaurants, and other businesses that would serve (*) African-American travelers. This institution used the submarine USS Barbero to test the feasibility of incorporating rockets into their standard services. Sears, Roebuck and Company\u2019s sales were bolstered through this institution\u2019s implementation of Rural Free Delivery. For 10 points, name this government institution that competes with FedEx and UPS in the delivery of letters and packages.",
            "answer": "United States Postal Service (accept United States Post Office, USPS, or United States Post Office Department)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The two main types of coins of this empire both depict an \u201carcher king\u201d and have yet to be found in the same archaeological context. A succession crisis in this empire forced many soldiers settled via the hatru system to mortgage their land to the Murashu family. The history of the trading House of Egibi was chronicled by five generations of its members, ending during the reign of this empire. The astronomer Kidinnu is believed to have lived under the rule of this empire. Contact with this empire brought the (*) kandys, a sleeved shirt, into fashion with the women of Athens, until supplanted by Spartan styles of dress. Herodotus wrote that \u201cneither by snow nor rain nor heat nor darkness\u201d could prevent the movement of mail along the Royal Road connecting Sardis to one of this empire\u2019s capitals. For 10 points, identify this empire founded by Cyrus the Great.",
            "answer": "Achaemenid Empire (prompt on \u201cPersia\u201d)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "In the preface to his translation of Kant\u2019s Critique of Pure Reason, one scholar claimed that it was the culmination of an intellectual tradition begun by this people. Scholarship on this people was used to justify government-backed branqueamento policies in Brazil around the turn of the 20th century. Arthur de Gobineau unfavorably compared the \u201cgentleman scholar\u201d ideal of China with the high-status of warriors among this people. Theozoology was the belief that this people were the descendants of (*) alien gods who bred using electricity. Max M\u00fcller lamented the use of his scholarship to support theories of the superiority of this people. Mortimer Wheeler claimed that \u201cIndra stands accused\u201d for an invasion supposedly carried out by this people. For 10 points, identify this people, the ancient progenitors of the Germans as claimed by the Third Reich.",
            "answer": "Aryans",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "While a student in this city, a poet was spurned romantically by Fred Amory and may have been sexually propositioned by W.H. Auden, whom he later wrote his senior thesis on. The play Try, Try! was premiered in this city\u2019s Poets\u2019 Theatre in 1951, and that premiere ended with a twenty-minute long rant by Thornton Wilder on the state of American theater. A bookshop that claims to be the \u201coldest continuous bookshop\u201d devoted to poetry, Grolier\u2019s, is located in this city, as well as the American Repertory Theater. A literary journal published in this city, the (*) Advocate, is the oldest college literary magazine in the US. Prominent members of the New York school of poetry, including Kenneth Koch, Frank O\u2019Hara and John Ashbery, met while attending college in this city. Libraries located in this city include Lamont and Widener, and current professors at a university in this city include Henry Louis Gates and former University President Lawrence Summers. For 10 points, name this city, which is home to Harvard University.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Cambridge",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "While on his way to exploring this river, John Ledyard accidentally took a lethal dose of sulfuric acid in an attempt to cure a \u201cbilious complaint\u201d. Jean Rouch, part of the first known expedition to travel the full length of this river, made the film Au pays de mages noirs about people living along it. The Soci\u00e9t\u00e9 de G\u00e9ographie\u2019s award for reaching a city along this river was claimed by Ren\u00e9 Cailli\u00e9. One explorer began two expeditions by traveling from the coast to (*) S\u00e9gou, a city on this river. The Landers brothers continued an earlier explorer\u2019s travels along this river by traveling from this river\u2019s delta to where that previous explorer had died at Bussa. Travels in the Interior of Africa contained the first description of this river written by a European who had seen it, and its author was Mungo Park. For 10 points, identify this West African river, along whose banks lies Timbuktu.",
            "answer": "Niger River",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "This empire\u2019s preparation for one battle was hindered by Alfa Bubakar ben Lanbar, a spy for the opposing force. An attack against this empire was preceded by the conquest of the Tuwat and Gurara Oases a decade before. He didn\u2019t live in Syria, but in honor of the short-term gains from attacking this empire, the ruler who ordered the campaign was dubbed al-Dhahabi, or \u201cthe Golden\u201d. The death of the final ruler of this empire, in retribution for the death of a company of fusiliers, is chronicled in a history of it called the Tarikh al-Fattash. Following its collapse, a prince of the last royal dynasty of this empire founded the (*) Dendi Kingdom. In one battle, the forces of this empire were run over by the cattle they had attempted to stampede into a Sa\u2019adi army led by Judar Pasha. This empire\u2019s last ruler Askia Ishaq was forced out of power by that loss at the Battle of Tondibi. For 10 points, identify this West African empire with a capital at Gao.",
            "answer": "Songhai Empire",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The steamship John D. Porter attempted to evacuate people from Memphis during an epidemic of this disease, but when nowhere would allow the passengers to disembark, the ship had to wander the Mississippi River for two months. Rival newspaper editors John Fenno and Benjamin Bache both died of this disease within four days of each other. Though proof would come later, Josiah Nott was the first person to link this disease with its means of transmission and lost four of his children to it in 1853. (*) Richard Allen was among those who ministered to people afflicted with this disease due to the supposed natural \u201cimmunity\u201d African-Americans had to it. That outbreak saw extensive use of bleeding and purging at the recommendation of Benjamin Rush. For 10 points, identify this mosquito-borne disease, an epidemic of which struck Philadelphia in 1793.",
            "answer": "yellow fever",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "ANSWER: yellow fever <AF> \u00a0 11. A book about this conflict describes the mixing of White, Black, and Indigenous peoples into \u201cracial bedrock\u201d as well as group dubbed the \u201cHercules-Quasimodos\u201d. The leader of one side in this conflict was born in Quixeramobim (\u201ckey\u201d-shay-rah-mo-\u201cbeam\u201d), died of dysentery after severe fasting, and had his brain preserved and analyzed by Dr. Nina Rodriguez. Monte Santo was a staging ground in this conflict, in which Colonel Tamarindo took command after the leader of one expedition, Moreira C\u00e9sar, was killed. Prudente de Morais was president of the country this conflict took place in, and one side believed in the return of a long-deceased King Sebastian. A militia known as the (*) Jagun\u00e7os played a major role in this conflict, which took place in a semi-arid caatinga (cah-ching-gah) region. Euclides da Cunha (COON-yuh) described this conflict in his book, Rebellion in the Backlands. For 10 points, name this 1896-97 conflict in the Brazilian state of Bahia (BAH-ee-uh) that was led by Anthony the Counselor.\u00a0",
            "answer": "War of Canudos (accept \u201cRebellion\u201d, \u201cRevolt\u201d, and other answers indicating armed conflict in place of \u201cWar\u201d; prompt on \u201cthe revolt of Anthony the Counselor\u201d, \u201cthe revolt of \u201cAnt\u00f4nio Conselheiro\u201d, and similar answers)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "This country was called an Antemurales Christianitatis, or \u201cBulwark of Christendom\u201d, in a letter congratulating Petar Berislavi\u010d for winning the Battle of Dubica (\u201cdue-beet\u201d-sah). This country\u2019s Hundred Years\u2019 War with the Ottomans is commonly claimed to have ended with its victory in the Battle of Sisak, one of whose leaders was the \u201cCarniolan Achilles\u201d Andreas von Auersperg. It\u2019s not Hungary, but the nobles of this country met in Cetin Castle to elect a new king after the death of Louis II at the Battle of Moh\u00e1cs. Nikola Zrinski, later known as the \u201cSlavic Leonidas\u201d, led a last-ditch charge out of the citadel of Szigetv\u00e1r (\u201cSEE-get\u201d-var) during the 1566 Turkish siege of the city while serving as (*) ban of this country. Ottoman influence in this country grew after the Republic of Ragusa came under the suzerainty of the Porte. For 10 points, name this country, whose centers for resistance against the Ottomans under the Habsburgs included its modern capital Zagreb.",
            "answer": "Croatia",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A referendum on this country\u2019s constitution was rigged with a system of white and black cards, leading to only 768 votes against it. Admiral Bancroft Gherardi attempted to intimidate this country into giving up territory, but his bluff was called by President Florvil Hyppolite after being advised by an anthropologist who had earlier written the book On the Equality of Human Races. Two of the three leaders of the First Pan-African Conference were from this country, B\u00e9nito Sylvain and Ant\u00e9nor Firmin. Militia known as the (*) Cacos operated in this country, and President Vilbrun Guillaume Sam, was murdered in this country after ordering the execution of political opponents like Oreste Zamor. While serving as minister to this country, Frederick Douglass was recalled in the M\u00f4le (MOLE-ay) Saint-Nicolas affair. For 10 points, name this country, the site of a US occupation from 1915 to 1934, which was once ruled by \u201cPapa Doc\u201d Duvalier.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Haiti",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "After a \u201cten-mile sendoff\u201d during this leader\u2019s funeral, a politician eulogized him as \u201copen and aboveboard\u201d and \u201cstrict in dissecting himself\u201d. The Ti\u0101nj\u012bn newspaper Yishi Bao funded this leader\u2019s years in France, and he co-founded an \u201cAwakening Society\u201d in the wake of the May Fourth movement. While in Sh\u00e0ngh\u0103i, he was nearly killed by B\u00e1i Ch\u00f3ngx\u01d0, and after the Marshall Mission failed, he fled to Y\u00e1n'\u0101n. This leader\u2019s (*) bladder cancer diagnosis was withheld by him for two years, contributing to his death. An attempt by the Gang of Four to suppress an outpouring of grief for this leader led to violent riots in the Ti\u0101n\u0101nm\u00e9n Incident. This leader peacefully settled the X\u012b'\u0101n incident, and he helped temper his superior\u2019s policies while implementing the Cultural Revolution. For 10 points, name this long-time ally of M\u00e1o Z\u00e9d\u014dng who served as the PRC\u2019s first Premier.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Zh\u014du \u0112nl\u00e1i [accept Chou1 En1-Lai2]",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "After a stint with the CBA Maine Lumberjacks, Billy Ray Bates joined this team. This team\u2019s physician Robert Cook was sued for negligent treatment by a former player for this team, and that player was traded away for Kevin Kunnert, Kermit Washington, and a first-round pick. Klay Thompson\u2019s dad, Mychal Thompson, was drafted with the number one pick by this team in 1978. Jack Ramsay\u2019s longest NBA coaching stint was with this team. This team\u2019s 1980 season was the subject of the book The Breaks of the Game by David Halberstam. In (*) 1977, this team won the NBA Finals behind the play of center Bill Walton. Clyde Drexler led this team to NBA Finals appearances in 1990 and 1992, and from 1988 to 2018 this team was owned by Paul Allen. For 10 points, name this west coast NBA team whose current players include CJ McCollum and Damian Lillard.\u00a0",
            "answer": "Portland Trail Blazers (accept either city or team name; accept Blazers)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "The ascetic Chi\u1e0dia Nathji (chee-ree-ah naht-jee) was apocryphally forcibly moved from a hill to build one of these places, a slight for which he cursed the state of the ruler who did so to be perpetually short of water. It is uncertain who constructed the Sher Mandal, located in one of these places, which was most famously used as a library. Paralleling their husbands\u2019 adherence to saka, women in these places would immolate themselves rather than face a successful enemy in a ritual called jauhar (\u201cjaw-her\u201d), perhaps most famously performed at (*) Chittor. A golden chain that commoners could shake to get the emperor\u2019s attention was supposedly set up in one of these places in Agra by Jahangir. For 10 points, what are these structures, a \u201cRed\u201d one of which was the residence of the Mughal emperors in Delhi?",
            "answer": "forts (accept Mughal or Rajput forts; accept castles; prompt on \u201cfortifications\u201d or other general types of defensive structures)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "Congressman Robert Broussard introduced a bill to Congress in 1910 to import these animals into Louisiana for their meat and to control an invasive plant species. One of these animals named Huberta walked from St. Lucia to East London between 1928 and 1931 before being shot by farmers. After being brought to London, one of these animals named Obaysch inspired a song called \u201c[this animal\u2019s] Polka\u201d. One of these animals named Vanessa is the among the growing feral population of these animals in (*) Colombia after they were imported to Pablo Escobar\u2019s Hacienda N\u00e1poles. Greek writers believed these animals could sweat blood, though it is now known that this is normal sweat with added protection against the diseases and sun of tropical Africa. For 10 points, name these large, semi-aquatic mammals, whose name comes from the Greek for \u201cwater horse\u201d.",
            "answer": "hippopotamuses",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A controversial photo in an issue of Life from 1944 depicts a woman gazing at one of these objects as she writes a thank you letter to her boyfriend. Statues found at the site of Roquepertuse may support Roman accounts of a Celtic cult surrounding these objects. An unfinished tower outside Cetinje [tseh-teen-nyeh] Monastery was used to display these objects. One people group processed these objects in order to control muisak spirits. Inspired by his military service in New Zealand, H.G. Robley acquired a large collection of these objects known to the M\u0101ori as (*) mokomakai. A type of these objects known as tsantsas were once created by the Shuar people. The Aztecs displayed these objects on tzompantli, which were often gathered from prisoners taken during flower wars. For 10 points, what were these objects that have historically been \u201chunted\u201d or \u201cshrunken\u201d?",
            "answer": "human heads (accept skulls or shrunken heads)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "A Zionist group in this country published a newspaper ad with the title \u201cFor Sale to Humanity 70,000 Jews, Guaranteed Human Beings at $50 a Piece\u201d in response to Romanian involvement in the Holocaust. The Rabbi\u2019s March attempted to convince this country\u2019s leader to aid European Jews, but that leader avoided the protesters by exiting from the rear of his residence for a weekend in the countryside. Various artists in this country organized the traveling pageant We Will Never Die to raise awareness of the plight of Jews under the Nazis. This country lessened its sanctions on Sweden for freely trading with Nazi Germany in exchange for Sweden sending (*) Raoul Wallenberg to Budapest to assist in the evacuation of its Jewish population. This country\u2019s efforts to avoid assisting Jews included being the second country after Cuba to deny the MS St. Louis entry. For 10 points, name this country that officially began assisting Holocaust victims with the establishment of the War Refugee Board under Franklin Roosevelt.",
            "answer": "United States of America (accept other common names)",
            "category": "History"
        },
        {
            "question": "An unidentified island in this body of water was supposedly named after Mar\u00eda de Lajara, who apocryphally drowned herself nearby out of impatience because the trip across this body of water was taking too long. Alessandro Malaspina led a Spanish scientific expedition in this body of water from 1789-1794, notable for being perhaps the first naval undertaking of its size with no cases of scurvy. A route across this body of water was discovered by Andr\u00e9s de Urdaneta. After an expedition crossing this body of water had many things (*) stolen by natives, Antonio Pigafetta called an island in this body of water the \u201cIsland of Thieves\u201d. Large quantities of silver were shipped across this body of water in yearly voyages from Acapulco. Traversed by the Manila Galleons, for 10 points, identify this body of water, whose eastern shore was first seen by Europeans under Vasco N\u00fa\u00f1ez de Balboa.",
            "answer": "Pacific Ocean (accept any named portion of the Pacific Ocean)",
            "category": "History"
        }
    ],
    "bonuses": []
}